## Joshua J. Hamilton

San Francisco Bay Area, CA, USA joshamilton@gmail.com 913-269-7789 https://www.linkedin.com/in/joshamilton/ https://github.com/joshamilton

# **Professional Summary**

Results-oriented data scientist harnessing complex data to improve the human condition, with eight years of experience
beyond the PhD. I built and led the data science group at Federation Bio, where I was responsible for designing, leading,
and executing data science projects from discovery to early clinical development. Effective leader and clear communicator
with the ability to prioritize competing objectives and align projects accordingly.

## Experience

#### • Data Scientist I, Data Scientist II, Sr Data Scientist, Federation Bio, Inc.

2019-present

- Built and led data science group of 3 FTEs and 2 contractors. Mentored research associates and scientists through multiple promotions in a matrix environment
- Led design and execution of data science efforts across the portfolio, for programs in metabolism, immunology, and oncology
- Partnered with CMC, translational medicine, clinical science, and regulatory affairs to advance discovery programs into clinical development. Served as technical expert in microbiome science and data science
- Communicated findings to internal and external stakeholders, in the form of research presentations, memos, and regulatory filings
- o Designed novel microbial communities to restore the functional capabilities of the healthy human microbiome
- Identified biomarkers and developed machine learning algorithms for detection of specific bacteria in complex microbial communities
- o Led internal and external cross-functional teams in development and qualification of bioanalytical assays
- Hired and managed contractors and CROs for projects in data science, bioinformatics, sequencing, and assay development
- o Designed and built bioinformatics pipelines for data QC, genome assembly, genome annotation, microbial phylogenetics, and metagenomic profiling, using Nextflow, Docker, R and Python
- Led development of custom software to enable reproducible and scalable data analysis, using R/Shiny
- Established best practices for data management and documentation. Authored policies and trained scientists to ensure data integrity and standardized reporting of study outcomes
- Launched laboratory informatics program by implementing Benchling ELN/LIMS, increasing throughput and decreasing TAT of scientific processes
- o Collaborated with IT to develop a data science architecture and manage buildout of infrastructure
- o Built and optimized cloud computing infrastructure, powered by AWS

### • Postdoctoral Research Associate, UW-Madison

2014-2019

- Identified molecular interactions within microbial communities, using a combination of experimental and computational methods, including:
  - \* Experimental: high-throughput experimental screens, metabolomics, genomics, and transcriptomics / RNA-Seq
  - \* Computational: bioinformatics (genome-centric metagenomics and metatranscriptomics) and metabolic modeling
- o Developed predictive models of microbial communities using differential equations modeling and machine learning
- Led development of genomic, transcriptomic, and metabolomic assays, authored laboratory protocols, and identified external service providers and collaborators
- Mentored graduate students in bioinformatics and software development, and fostered adoption of good data management practices among laboratory members and collaborators
- o Participated in build out of anaerobic microbiology lab, including anaerobic chambers and liquid handling robots

#### • Graduate Research Assistant, UW-Madison

2009-2014

- o Published multiple metabolic reconstructions and genome-scale metabolic models
- Developed algorithm to identify functional differences between microbes using comparative genomics and metabolic modeling
- o Incorporated thermodynamic information into metabolic models using chemoinformatic group contribution methods

Hamilton Résumé 1 of 2 Last revised: August 2023

### **Skills**

- Soft skills: leadership, cross-functional collaboration, communication, writing, presentations
- Programming and Software Development: R, Python, Git, Github, Nextflow, Docker, AWS
- Bioinformatics: genome assembly, genome annotation, metagenomic assembly and binning, metagenome profiling, 16S rRNA sequencing, amplicon sequencing
- Drug development: drug discovery, assay development, preclinical research, translational research, early clinical development

### Education

University of Wisconsin-Madison (UW-Madison)

Ph.D., Chemical Engineering

Case Western Reserve University (CWRU)

B.S., Chemical Engineering

Madison, WI 2014

Cleveland, OH

2009

### **Selected Patents and Publications**

- Swem LR, Kumar P, Bhalla A, Tripathi SA, Parmar A, Hamilton JJ, Brumbaugh AR, Ricci DP, Layman HRW, Ciglar AM, Berleman J, Walters Z, Jacoby K, Youngblut ND, Grauer A, Drabant Conley E, Romasko H (2023) Microbial consortia. US Patent Application No. 18/060,831.
- 13. Swem L, Ricci D, Brumbaugh AR, Cremin J, **Hamilton JJ**, Tripathi S, Wong L, Romasko H, Bracken R, Drabant Conley E. (2023) *Microbial consortia for the treatment of disease*. US Patent Application No. 17/906,060.
- 12. Ricci D, **Hamilton JJ**, Tripathi S, Brumbaugh A, Cremin J, Ou N, Layman H, and L Swem. (2022) *Creation of Rationally Designed and Metabolically Active Microbiome Consortia for Treatment of Enteric Hyperoxaluria*. Kidney International Reports. 7(2): S204-S205. doi:10.1016/j.ekir.2022.01.490.
- Clark RL, Connors B, Stevenson DM, Hromada SE, Hamilton JJ, Amador-Noguez D, and OS Venturelli. (2021) Design of synthetic human gut microbiome assembly and function. Nature Communications. 12: 3254. doi:10.1038/s41467-021-22938-y.
- Scarborough MJ, Hamilton JJ, Erb EA, Donohue TJ, and DR Noguera. (2020) Diagnosing and Predicting Mixed-Culture Fermentations with Unicellular and Guild-Based Metabolic Models. mSystems. 5(5):e00755-20. doi:10.1128/mSystems.00755-20.
- 9. Cao X\*, **Hamilton JJ\***, and OS Venturelli. (2019) *Understanding and Engineering Distributed Biochemical Pathways in Microbial Communities*. Biochemistry. 58(2): 94-107. doi:10.1021/acs.biochem.8b01006.
- 8. Scarborough MJ, Lawson CE, **Hamilton JJ**, Donohue TJ, and DR Noguera. (2018) *Metatranscriptomic and Thermodynamic Insights into Medium-Chain Fatty Acid Production Using an Anaerobic Microbiome*. mSystems. 3(6): e00221-18. doi:10.1128/mSystems.00221-18.
- 7. Rohwer RR, **Hamilton JJ**, Newton, RJ, and KD McMahon. (2018) *TaxAss: Leveraging a Custom Freshwater Database Achieves Fine-Scale Taxonomic Resolution*. mSphere. 3(5): e00327-18. doi:10.1128/mSphere.00327-18.
- 6. **Hamilton JJ**, Garcia SL, Brown BS<sup>†</sup>, Oyserman BO, Moya F, Bertilsson S, Malmstrom RR, Forest KT, and KD McMahon. (2017) *Metabolic Network Analysis and Metatranscriptomics Reveals Auxotrophies and Nutrient Sources of the Cosmopolitan Freshwater Microbial Lineage acl.* mSystems. 2(4): e00091-17. doi:10.1128/mSystems.00091-17.
- Lawson CE, Wu S, Bhattacharjee AS, Hamilton JJ, McMahon KD, Goel R, and DR Noguera. (2017) Metabolic network analysis reveals microbial community interactions in anammox granules. Nature Communications. 8: 15416. doi:10.1038/ncomms15416.
- 4. **Hamilton JJ**, Calixto Contreras M<sup>†</sup>, and JL Reed. (2015) *Thermodynamics and H*<sub>2</sub> *Transfer in a Methanogenic, Syntrophic Community.* PLoS Computational Biology. 11(7): e1004364. doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004364.
- 3. **Hamilton JJ** and JL Reed. (2014) *Software platforms to facilitate reconstructing genome-scale metabolic networks*. Environmental Microbiology. 16(1): 49-59. doi:10.1111/1462-2920.12312.
- 2. **Hamilton JJ**, Dwivedi V<sup>†</sup>, and JL Reed. (2013) *Quantitative Assessment of Thermodynamic Constraints on the Solution Space of Genome-Scale Metabolic Models*. Biophysical Journal. 105(2): 512-522. doi:10.1016/j.bpj.2013.06.011.
- 1. **Hamilton JJ** and JL Reed. (2012) *Identification of Functional Differences in Metabolic Networks Using Comparative Genomics and Constraint-Based Models*. PLoS ONE. 7(4): e34670. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0034670.

Hamilton Résumé 2 of 2 Last revised: August 2023

<sup>\*</sup> indicates equal contribution

<sup>†</sup> indicates an undergraduate student author